Finding aid to the James Parker records, 1924-2005 Archives.Parker.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
James Parker records, 1910-2005
Bulk, 1951-1993
1910-2005, n.d.
Archives.Parker.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
37.5 Linear feet (89 boxes, 1030 folders)
James Parker (1924-2001) began his career as a specialist in European decorative arts at The Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1951, was appointed assistant curator in 1954, associate curator in 1962 and curator in 1968. He was appointed Curator Emeritus in 1993, upon his retirement from the Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts (ESDA). He specialized in French and English furniture. The James Parker Records include correspondence and memoranda, research notes, clippings and photographic materials that document Parker’s significant contributions to the Museum and to the field of European decorative arts. These records document the internal activities of ESDA and elucidate Parker’s vigorous work on major Museum acquisitions, publications, exhibitions, permanent gallery installations, and most significantly, his tireless research activities.
Parker, James, 1924-
Scope and Contents note
The James Parker records include correspondence, research notes and reference materials, clippings, memoranda, blueprints, and photographic materials that document Parker’s contributions to The Metropolitan Museum of Art and to the field of European decorative arts. These records document the internal activities of the Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts (ESDA) and elucidate Parker’s vigorous work on major Museum acquisitions, publications, exhibitions, permanent gallery installations, and most significantly, his tireless research activities.
The majority of the records consist of Parker’s extensive index card and research files that demonstrate his extraordinarily thorough and intricate system for documenting the universe of European decorative art and those who collected it. The “Research” series comprises almost eighty percent of the collection, the bulk of which includes Parker’s card file system. Other research materials were classified as either “General” or “Collections,” if the material pertains to specific collections of art objects.
Parker devoted an enormous amount of time to the installation refurbishment, and renovation of permanent gallery spaces. However, the “Galleries” series is the smallest and it encompasses those few documents which were not dispersed among departmental files, and do not pertain to the thirteen Wrightsman Galleries for French decorative arts.
Correspondence can be found throughout every series; however, several professional colleagues at other institutions, including Henry Sorensen, Pierre Verlet, and F.J.B. Watson, with whom Parker corresponded over the course of numerous decades have been placed in a separate “Correspondence” series.
The collection includes a few personal and family documents, including copies of Parker’s military discharge documents, financial records, and birth certificate. Materials relating to many objects eventually acquired by the Museum are present throughout the collection. When it has been possible to identify these, a note including the object accession number has been added to the relevant entry in the Container List, or written on the folder.
All materials were removed from their original card catalog drawers, file folders and notebook binders and rehoused in folders appropriate for their format. For the most part, Parker’s headings were retained; untitled files were supplied with titles, and these appear within brackets in the finding aid. Almost all photographic materials have miscellaneous materials (MM), accession, inventory, or catalogue entry numbers penciled on the back. The research material compiled by Parker range in date and origin throughout the records- and amassing these resources was a decades-long effort. All individual folders within the subseries “Card File” and numerous others within the “Research” series are, therefore, undated. Many research materials, correspondence, memoranda and notations are not originals, but were compiled by Parker in photocopy-form.
The James Parker records represent a fraction of Parker’s correspondence, notes, and reference materials which have also been dispersed among departmental administrative and object file folders and within his personal library materials, now separately cataloged and located in the European Sculpture and Decorative Arts library.
Related Archival Materials note
James Parker Correspondence Files, Office of the Secretary Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Oral history interview with James Parker, 1994 Aug. 9 -19, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
The department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts (ESDA) may have additional documentation regarding the art objects, gallery installations, or donors that are the subject of correspondence and research material in this collection. Consult ESDA staff for further information.
Arrangement note
The James Parker Records are organized in the following five series: I. Research, II. Galleries, III. Wrightsman Collection [Museum staff access only], IV. Correspondence, and V. Biographical Materials.
Resources are arranged alphabetically by subject, personal name, or corporate name. The original arrangement of the series “Research” was maintained during processing. In all other series, dated materials were arranged in ascending chronological order.
Series I. Research I.A. Card File I.B. General I.C. Collections Series II. Galleries Series III. Wrightsman Collection [Museum staff access only] Series IV. Correspondence Series V. Biographical Materials
Biographical Note
James Parker (1924-2001) began his career as a specialist in European decorative arts at The Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1951, was appointed assistant curator in 1954, associate curator in 1962 and curator in 1968. He was appointed Curator Emeritus in 1993, upon his retirement. He specialized in French and English furniture. He was once described by a colleague as a “curator’s curator,” who quietly inspired his associates as his duties developed and expanded over the course of his four-decade career. His work entailed fastidious research, and resulted in copious notes and an abundance of decorative arts research materials that he gathered, organized, and indexed.
Parker’s father, Cortlandt Parker, was a major general in the United States Army and his paternal grandfather, James Parker, served as a general as well. Both had distinguished, decorated careers in the military. His maternal grandfather, Morris Gray, had served as president of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts from 1914 to 1924. Parker was born in Boston, but due to his father's military career, his formative years were spent in many places, including Vermont, England, Hawaii, and Massachusetts. After enrolling at Harvard University to study modern European history in 1942, his college career was interrupted by a nearly two-year stint with the 38th Division of Army Field Artillery in the Pacific region. Following the end of World War II, he returned to Harvard and received his degree in 1948.
Heeding the advice of the Metropolitan’s director, Francis Henry Taylor, Parker traveled abroad in 1948 to gain experience by working as an apprentice in museums across Europe. He divided the next two years interning at the Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris, the Louvre, Paris and the Victoria and Albert Museum, London. He also briefly assisted at Wiesbaden Collecting Point, a World War II restitution archival depot for recovered art objects in Germany. He enjoyed his time abroad immensely, studying under such luminaries as Pierre Verlet and Sir John Pope-Hennessey, art historians and curators at the Louvre and the Victoria and Albert, respectively. Upon his return to the States in 1951, Parker joined the Department of Renaissance and Modern Art, the decorative arts contingent of the Metropolitan- led by Preston Remington, as a curatorial assistant. In 1954 he was appointed assistant curator and in 1962 associate curator. The department name changed to Renaissance and Post-Renaissance Art (1957-1962) and to Western European Arts (1962-1978) under the leadership of John Goldsmith Phillips. In 1968, Parker was elected curator, a position he held until his retirement in 1993, when he was elected Curator Emeritus. The department continued to evolve, adopting its current nomenclature European Sculpture and Decorative Arts, and appointing Olga Raggio as chair of the department in 1971. She was the first woman to hold the post, and remained in the position until 2001.
Parker’s specialization in French furnishings and interiors of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, earned him a guiding role in installing The Wrightsman Galleries, an extraordinary ensemble of period rooms. These spaces, of which were actual rooms taken from historic buildings and some recreations intended to show related works of decorative art in an authentic setting, reflect the unparalleled and encyclopedic collection of French decorative arts of two of the Museum’s greatest patrons, Charles and Jayne Wrightsman. This project occupied Parker for the better part of three decades, as various rooms were installed, refurbished and reinstalled. In 2007, the galleries’ technical infrastructure was modernized, the lighting revamped, and the objects rearranged; yet Parker’s meticulous research and work is still evident, and the galleries are among the Museum’s most renowned installations.
In addition to the French period rooms, Parker supervised the installation of a number of permanent spaces devoted to English and German objects. He also played a crucial role in seamlessly integrating into the galleries collections of objects amassed and donated to the Museum by Marion E. Cohn, Lesley G. and Emma A. Sheafer, Judge Irwin Untermyer, Madame Lilliana W. Teruzzi, Jack and Belle Linsky and the Samuel H. Kress Foundation, among others.
Parker wrote scores of articles on subjects ranging from Rococo furniture to gilt-bronze ornaments, as well as assisting in the research and writing for several publications devoted to the Kress, Sheafer and Wrightsman collections. He lectured and served as an adjunct professor at New York University. Parker felt that the decorative arts were, in a sense, an undiscovered realm and he set out to diligently answer questions unasked within the field. His meticulous research efforts and concern for historic interiors and objects led to important findings. It was Parker, for example, who discovered that the Sagredo bedroom windows had originally been located on the opposite wall, but were interchanged during installation and relocation to allow for natural and then electric light. He truly considered the importance of adaptation and original intention with regards to Museum installations, and he attempted to impart that knowledge whenever possible. He always shared his extensive knowledge with his colleagues whether through one-on-one encounters or by way of his meticulously annotated files.
Parker died on June 20, 2001 and was survived by nieces Elizabeth K. Parker and Nancy Gray Parker Wilson, and nephews, Cortlandt Jr. and Stephen Ward; as well as fourteen grandnieces and nephews.
Selected Chronology
1924 Born in Boston, MA on January 22nd to Elizabeth Gray, of Boston and Cortlandt Parker, of Newark, New Jersey. Cortlandt Parker’s military career commenced upon his graduation from West Point in 1906. This led to James Parker’s itinerant childhood, and an initial upbringing at military bases Fort Myer, Virginia and Washington D.C.
1931-1933 Attended day school in London, England.
1933-1935 Attended Stanmore Park in Middlesex, England.
1936 Cortlandt Parker stationed at Fort Ethan Allen in Vermont. James Parker attended day school nearby.
1936-1938 Attended Punahoe School in Oahu, Hawaii.
1938-1942 Attended St. Mark’s School in Southborough, Massachusetts.
1942-1943 Enrolled at Harvard University in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
1943 Enlisted in the Army. Spent two years, seven months and twenty-one days in military service, most of it in field artillery, the branch to which his father devoted his career. Spent nine months in the continental United States (including basic training at Fort Bragg, North Carolina), one year and ten months in the Pacific theater on shipboard, in garrison and in action (from January 29 to August 14, 1945 on Luzon Island, Philippines).
1945 Honorably discharged as a Technician, Fifth Grade after twenty-two months of service with the 150th Field Artillery Battalion of the 38th National Guard Division in December. Upon disembarkment, he was greeted by his father, then general commandant in charge of the Southern Defense Command, in Los Angeles, California.
1946 Reenrolled at Harvard University as an undergraduate in February.
1948 Awarded his bachelor’s degree in modern European history in June.
1948 Interviewed at The Metropolitan Museum of Art in October. Encouraged by director Francis Henry Taylor to work abroad in European museums to gain experience to qualify for a position in the decorative arts department at the Museum.
1948-1949 Served four months as an apprentice at the Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris and six months in the Département des Objets d’Art of the Louvre Museum under curator Pierre Verlet.
1949 Starting in November, worked at the Victoria and Albert Museum, London for nine months as an apprentice-assistant (six months in the Department of Architecture and Sculpture, two months in the Department of Furniture and Woodwork, and one month in the Department of Ceramics).
1950 Spent July to September at the Central Collecting Point in Wiesbaden, Germany, where works of art confiscated by the Third Reich had been sorted and dispersed.
1950 Relocated to New York, New York.
1951 Employed at the Metropolitan as an assistant in the Renaissance and Modern Art Department on January 2nd.
1954 Appointed assistant curator on July 1st.
1962 Appointed associate curator on July 1st.
1968 Appointed curator on June 13th.
1993 Retired at age 69 on June 30th.
1993 Elected Curator Emeritus, Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts on September 14th.
2001 Died of cancer at age seventy-seven on June 20th.
Works Consulted
Draper, James David. “A life at The Met: James Parker and the collecting of Italian furniture.” Apollo, January 1993, 20-24.
Dulling, Corey. “James Parker, at 77; was Met curator for 4 decades.” Boston Globe, June 24, 2001, A25.
Johnson, Ken. “Gilding the Ancien Régime.” New York Times, November 9, 2007, E44. Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Period rooms in The Metropolitan Museum of Art. (New York: The Museum: H.N. Abrams, 1996).
Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). “Recent Deaths: James Parker, Curator Emeritus, European Sculpture and Decorative Arts.” The biweekly: A newsletter for the Staff and Volunteers of The Metropolitan Museum of Art, July 6, 2001, 6.
Oral History Project interview with James Parker, August 9, 12, 19, 1994, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Parker, James. “J. Parker’s Report on his World War II Army Service 7/3/87.” Photocopy, Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts, Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.
Vogel, Carol. “James Parker, 77, Curator of European Decorative Arts at the Met.” New York Times, June 23, 2001, A11.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for research. Series I, boxes 71-72; Series III; and Series V, box 89 are open to research by Museum staff only.
Custodial History note
The James Parker records were transferred from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts to the Museum Archives in 2013.
Dauterman, Carl Christian, 1908-1989; Hoentschel, Georges; Kress, Samuel H., (Samuel Henry), 1863-1955 -- Art collections; Lesley and Emma, Sheafer -- Art collections; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Department of Decorative Arts.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Department of European Sculpture and Decorative Arts.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Department of Renaissance and Modern Art .; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). Department of Renaissance and Post-Renaissance Art.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). -- Employees; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913; Sorensen, Henry; Untermyer, Irwin; Verlet, Pierre; Watson, F. J. B., (Francis John Bagott), 1907-1992; Wrightsman, Charles B.; Wrightsman, Jayne; Administrative records; Art museum curators.; Art, French--18th century--Catalogs; Clippings (Books, newspapers etc.); Correspondence; Decorative arts; Decorative arts--Collectors and collecting; Decorative arts--Europe; Period rooms; Photographs; Sculpture, European; Slides (Photographs).
- Series I. Research, 1912-1997, n.d.; 31.0 Linear feet (72 boxes, 839 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Parker utilized a wide range of resources to conduct his curatorial studies and compiled an extensive collection of reference materials, primarily concerned with Western European decorative arts. Subseries designations are largely reflective of the manner in which he stored and arranged his material. The primary difference between the two initial subseries lies in the fact that Parker chose to organize his “card file” materials folded and filed inside of actual card catalogue drawers and his “general” materials in notebook binders and file folders. The materials within subseries “card file” and “general” are of a similar nature and subject matter, and in fact, often overlap. Both of these subseries are organized by category, with subdivisions for geography, time period, or personal names. The third subseries “collections” was also contained in notebook binders, although its subject matter is specific to collectors, both institutional and personal, and includes many ESDA objects.
  Source materials range in date and origin, and amassing these resources was a decades-long effort; therefore, all individual folders within “card file” and several within “general” and “collections” subseries are undated.
  The “card file” subseries consists primarily of handwritten notations penciled on to three-by-five paper slips and annotated clippings from serials, monographs and auction catalogs. Preservation photocopies were created in most instances. In addition to these research materials, the subseries includes postcards, correspondence and memoranda, rubbings, photographs, negatives and slides. The “general” subseries contains similar materials, with the exception of paper slip notations. In addition, the subseries also includes transparencies, inventories, offprints and publicity materials. The majority of the “collections” subseries comprises photographs, although invoices, correspondence and memoranda and research materials also appear.
  Arrangement note
  This series contains three subseries: I.A. Card File, I.B. General and I.C. Collections.
  Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject, preserving Parker’s organizational scheme. Supplied folder titles appear in brackets. All material in the “card file” subseries was filed in the order found, regardless of date, within folders. All dated material within folders in subseries “general” and “collections” is arranged in ascending chronological order. Photographic materials are filed as found. Almost all have MM or accession numbers penciled on the back.
  - Subseries I.A. Card File, 1922-1933, 1943-1950, 1957-1996, n.d.; 25.0 Linear feet (60 boxes, 722 folders)
    This subseries consists of handwritten notations and annotated clippings from serials, monographs and auction catalogs, originally folded and stored in 129 3x5in. card catalogue drawers. Preservation photocopies have been created for all of Parker’s notes, previously written in pencil on fragile slips of three-by-five paper. Depending on the number of slips in each subject area, somewhere between one and four have been reproduced on each 8½ x 11in. sheet. In cases in which information was written on both sides of a slip, each side was reproduced accordingly to reflect its recto-verso relationship. The majority of the slips pertain to bibliographic sources in the study of the decorative arts; specific quotations, auction lots and departmental objects are also cited.
    Correspondence and memoranda with, to and from Parker has been noted throughout. Individuals’ institutional affiliations are noted where known. The numerous postcards interspersed throughout the subseries were compiled by Parker for their images. Any writing on the postcards is incidental. The inclusion of photographs, negatives, slides and other noteworthy research materials are also noted. Similar research materials maintained by Parker in notebook binders and file folders, rather than card catalogue drawers, comprise the subseries “general.”
    Parker’s original headings and arrangement have been retained. The records have been removed from 3 x 5in. index drawers and placed in folders by subject, of which there are 61, the largest being “furniture.” All original subject headings were retained and utilized as folder titles. Specific individuals and places occasionally warrant their own, or multiple folders. In most instances, the initial materials under a particular subject heading contain basic, general information related to that topic. All materials within were filed as found, regardless of dated materials.
    Folders are alphabetically arranged by subject matter and nationality. Each subject may also be further divided by time period, alphabetically arranged by the name of collector, dealer or maker or alphabetically arranged by geographical name.
    To indicate geographic origin, nationalities are used in lieu of proper nouns (e.g. English, Finnish), with the exception of the United States of America (U.S.A.). References to nation-states no longer in existence have been retained (e.g. Czechoslovakian, Yugoslavian).
    The subject “topography and descriptive” contains material relating to architecture, interiors, domestic dwellings and landscapes of all types. “Includes” indicates a specific heading assigned by Parker. “Cites” signifies Parker merely mentioned the entity on several materials. The term “mixed” indicates that the enclosed materials pertain to objects on which multiple makers collaborated. The term “various” is employed when numerous makers are referred to. All “see also” references are Parker’s.
    - Academies. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Note: Includes English. French. Italian. U.S.A.
    - Addresses. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Note: Contains business cards or contact information for furniture restorers, craftsmen, personal contacts, etc.
    - Appraisers. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Note: Contains 1 photograph.
    - Architecture. A - D. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Note: Includes Austrian. Belgian. Dutch.
    - Architecture. English (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Note: Includes A - Z.
    - Architecture. English (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Architecture. French (1 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Architecture. French (2 of 2). (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Architecture. G - Ir. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Note: Includes German. Irish.
    - Architecture. Italian. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Architecture. P - S. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Note: Includes Polish. Portuguese. Russian. Scottish. Spanish. Swedish.
    - Architecture. U.S.A. Box 1, Folder 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Arms and iconology. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      See also: Series I. Research / Subseries I.A. Card File / f. Topographical and Descriptive Painting.
    - Arms and iconology. A - D. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arms and iconology. English. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Arms and iconology. French. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Arms and iconology. G - Ir. (Box 1, Folder 17)